<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A godly and shorte treatise of the sacraments. vvritten by Robert Some..</title>
            <author>Some, Robert, 1542-1609.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22906</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1136</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">21429148</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 21429148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12589)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1736:7, 2355:6a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A godly and shorte treatise of the sacraments. vvritten by Robert Some..</title>
                  <author>Some, Robert, 1542-1609.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[92] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Geo. Bish.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1582..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Colophon imprint: Imprinted at London at the Three Cranes in the Vintree, by Thomas Dawson, for George Byshoppe. 1582.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁸ F⁶.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border; initials.</note>
                  <note>Bound with an incomplete copy of STC 16814.5 following.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of original in the British Library (same copy filmed twice).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacraments --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Godly and ſhorte</hi> Treatiſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s.</p>
            <p>VVritten by <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Some.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>By one ſpirite are we all baptiſed into one body, whether Iewes or Grecians, whether bond or free: and haue bin all made to drinke into one ſpirit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Corinth. chap. <hi>12.</hi> verſe. <hi>13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> for Geo. Biſh.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno.</hi> 1582.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:2"/>
            <head>To the right honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>&amp; his very good Lord</hi> &amp; maſter, the Lord Robert Dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley Earle of Leiceſter, Baron of Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigh, knight of the moſt noble order of the gatter, Maiſter of the Queenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Horſes, and one of her highneſſe moſt honourable priuie Counſell, Robert Some wiſheth increaſe of Gods giftes by Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath pleaſed God to deale verie graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with your L. your thankfulneſſe to his Maieſtie wil nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly appeare, if you goe on in doing your beſt for the increaſe of Gods religion. The high way to compaſſe this, is the calling for, and placing of ſuch in the lande, as by gods bleſſing are able and willing to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite his Church. When fitt men are found out they muſt haue both defence &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance:
<pb facs="tcp:23978:3"/>defence, that for well doing they be not diſcouraged: maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that they may attende vpon Gods ſeruice without diſtraction of minde. If this were put in practiſe, almightie God ſhould bee better ſerued then he is, and our gracious ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Queene Elizabeth more heartely obeyed then ſhee is. Howe ſinglie many parts of this realm are furniſhed with tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, all the worlde doth ſee: the enemie with great ioy, the godly with great grief. The cauſe of this miſchiefe is either great want of iudgement, or great corruption in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which do preferre, &amp; are preferred to eccleſiaſticall liuings. The firſt of theſe is a groſe fault, but the latter is intollerable ſin, as is manifeſtly proued in the nexte leafe after this epiſtle. Our Vniuerſities both haue and do bread vp many excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and may well be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to the Apple tree of Perſia, which in good meſure doth bud, bloſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; beare fruit al times of the yere. Before that ſtudents do come to excellent paſſe, their paines and charges are verie great, for without labour and Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, learning is not come by, and without expence, ſtudie cannot be maintayned.</p>
            <p>When ſtudents are furniſhed with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="tcp:23978:3"/>are they prouided for? is good done to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the churches greater good? it is verie cleare that they are ſingly rewarded, and the caſe of manie both in the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities &amp; abroad doth ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proue this. But anſwere peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture wilbe made that theſe ſtudentes muſt vſe meanes for their preferment. If by meanes we vnderſtande coaſting vp &amp; down y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey for liuings,<note place="margin">Iudg. chap. <hi>17.</hi> verſe <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> practiſe of Michahs prieſt, &amp; is at no ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to be liked of: if by meanes be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood either buying of places right out, or departing with ſome part of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, it is a grieuous plague, &amp; muſt bee taken head of: for it infecteth both the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, &amp; the giuer, &amp; ſome other partes of the Church of God: the taker, becauſe it maketh him thinke vily of religion, when he ſees &amp; feeles y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corruption of a teacher: the giuer, for beſids the preſent ſhipwrack of a good conſcience, he is driuen to ſell deare becauſe he bought deare: the church of God, for it peſters it with vnfit &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt both teachers &amp; gouernours, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by gods honor is greatly defaced, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good ſubiects of the land, very greuouſly offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. I may add to this, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this miſchief, if it
<pb facs="tcp:23978:4"/>not in time meete with, will be the vndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Cambridge and Oxford, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently bring forth Barbariſme.<note place="margin">Gene. cha. <hi>47</hi> verſe. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> The prieſtes of Egypt were carefully prouided for in the time of famine, and ſhall a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our learned preachers almoſt famiſh in the floriſhing eſtate of the realme of England? The popiſh ſort are very carefull that the Popes plough goe forwarde, they ſpare neither coſt not labour to increaſe ſuperſtition. Howe bountifully their prieſts are dealt with euery man may ſee, and their liberalitie doth more hurt Gods religion, then we are aware of. Shall they prouide extraordinarilie for theirs, and ſhall ourgodly and learned ſtudents not haue that prouiſion which of right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto them? they which are ſeruante to any me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of trade, are after a time in caſe to maintaine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues &amp; theirs, and ſhall the vniuerſitie diuines after many yeeres ſtudie and great expenſe, be compelied for want of maintenance either to commend themſelues to the ſtaffe and waller, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelues to ſome other courſe? ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeruants in court, for a litle and meane ſeruice receiue great good of their Lordes and maſters charge, &amp; what haue the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes
<pb facs="tcp:23978:4"/>committed not to haue prouiſion of their own, that is to ſay, of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches charge. Good my L. te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts caſes, &amp; ſeing almighy God hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement for their defence and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, haue good care eſpecially of ſuch as are furniſhed by almightie God for the comfort of his Churche. If your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip worke the good of theſe (which I do and will pray for) you ſhall do God great ſeruice, &amp; he wil multiplie his bleſſings &amp; fauour vpon you. As for them which are guilty of corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either by taking or gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing money, becauſe their ſinne is very great, they muſt firſt make reſtitution of money, &amp; Church liuings, vngraciouſlye come by, &amp; then craue pardon humblie as almightie Gods handes for theſe groſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normities.</p>
            <p>This order which I preſcribe is gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and therefore with al reuerence to his Maieſtie muſt be liked of. If reſtitution be not made by ſuch as are in caſe to doe it, their repentance is no repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they looke for at gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds will not be grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I beſeech almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God either to giue theſe men vnfained repentance of his great mercy for the leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:23978:5"/>hurt of the church, or to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his iuſtice for the greater good of his church.<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>54.</hi> ad Macedomum. Nehem. chap. <hi>5.</hi> verſe <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> And as to Nehemias praier in another caſe of oppreſſion, the Lords people ſaid Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo I doubt not but your Lorſhip and all which feare God both in the court, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of this land, wil ſay many a har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to this praier of mine, againſt the ſpoyle of both church &amp; vniuerſities.</p>
            <p>I did preſent to your L. when I waited on your honor in the court, a latin Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it pleaſd you to take it in good part, I am now bold to offer to your L. a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for another teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my dutiful mind. If it ſhal pleaſe you to peruſe it, I doubt neither of your profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by it, nor of your good accepting of it. The ſtuffe in this treatiſe is very ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and hath in it varietie inough for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of ſo ſhort a writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Thus deſiring almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God to increaſe his good gifts in your L. for the great good of this noble land, &amp; for your own ſinguler comfort, I take my leaue of your good L. in moſt humble ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. At Cambridge the 15. of May. 1582.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Chap. Robert Some.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Church liuinges</hi> may not bee taken from <hi>godly and learned miniſter, but</hi> muſt be freely beſtowed vpon them.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ill a man</hi> ſpoyle his Gods?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Malac. chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 8.9.</note> yet haue yee ſpoyled me: but yee ſay, wherin haue we ſpoyled thee? in tythes &amp; offrings: ye are curſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a curſe, for yee haue ſpoiled me &amp;c. ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord. If almighty God was robbed of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in the time of the law, when tythes and offrings were not brought into his ſtorehouſe for the maintenance of his ſeruice, and for the reliefe of the prieſts &amp; poore amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is a neceſſary co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent, that Gods honour is greatlye impayred by them, which pull from the Church any part of that which is giuen for the vpholding of Gods religion, and therefore that they are accurſed.</p>
            <p>Let him that is taught in the worde make him that hath taught him<note place="margin">Galath. chap. <hi>6.</hi> ver. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:23978:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>partaker of all his goods. If the ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt commaund vs to giue of our owne goods to our teachers, then wee may not ſpoyle them of the Churches goods.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Samuel</hi> deſcribing the conditions of an vſurping king,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam. chap.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 15.</note> ſetteth downe this for one, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites: he will take the tenth of your ſeede &amp; of your vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and giue it vnto his Eunuches and ſeruantes. If the king might not take the tenthes of ſeede and vineyards,<note place="margin">Nomb. chap. <hi>18.</hi> ver. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> becauſe they were dewe to the prieſtes by Gods owne order and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the maintenance of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, no man hath any priuiledge to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich him ſelfe, his child, or ſeruants with the ſpoyle of Churche lyuinges, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king money or penſions for preferring other to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The elders</hi> of the Iewes deſired Chriſt inſtantly to heale the Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turions ſeruant:<note place="margin">Luke. chap. <hi>7.</hi> ver. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> their reaſon was this, he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth our nation and hath built vs a ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue. If the building of a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for the Iewes godly aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies, was an argument of the Centurions loue
<pb facs="tcp:23978:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto that nation, the pulling away of that from the Churche and Churche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which woulde mainteyne godlie and Chriſtian aſſemblies, is a ſure ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument that little care is had eyther of Gods honour, or of his Miniſters, or of Gods people, or of any religion at all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezechias</hi> the king of Iuda con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that the Prieſtes and Leuites ſhould be throughly prouided for by the people of Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro. chap.</hi> 31. <hi>ver,</hi> 4.</note> that they might be incouraged in the lawe of the Lorde, that is to ſay, that they might cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without diſtraction of mynde at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend vppon their calling. If it was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in Ezechias time that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Ieruſalem ſhoulde haue mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance at the hands of the nobility and Citizens of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is moſt equall, that none in our time whatſoeuer ſhould take to themſelues, eyther the whole or part of ſuch maintenance, as hath beene heeretofore prouided for the Miniſters, and is nowe confirmed to them by the godlie lawes of this noble lande.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If Dauid refuſed</hi> to drinke of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Bethlehem becauſe it was gotten with daunger of loſing a few temporall liues,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Chro. chap. <hi>11.</hi> ver. <hi>16.17.18.19.</hi>
               </note> it is a very great ſinne by praying vpon the church liuinges (as a hawke doth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partriches) to ſpoyle Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> food of their ſoules, &amp; ſo to bring a plague of famine amongſt them. If Dauid deſerue commendation for pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out the water of Bethlehem to the lord for a ſacrifice, what do they deſerue which by pulling from the Church and Churchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do ſpoyle almighty God of his ſeruice &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore of neceſſary releif, which are groſſe ſinnes againſt both the tables of the commaundements.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If anie</hi> faithfull man or faithfull woman haue widowes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim. chap. 5. ver. 16.</note> let them mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto them and let not the Churche be charged, that there may be ſufficient for them that are widowes in deed. If they ſinne which for the eaſe of their owne purſes ſuffer the Churche to bee charged, their ſinne is greater which do pull from the Churche, or take eyther mony or penſions of the Church men for preferring of them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>If God doe</hi> curſe,<note place="margin">Deut. chap. <hi>27.</hi> ver. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> and all good men deteſt them which remoue the bounde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, becauſe by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fact, quarrels growe amongſt neighbors, &amp; other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s land is ſomtimes vniuſtly come by, they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a more greeuous curſe at Gods hands, &amp; vnder greater deteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at his peoples hands, which take away either landes or commodities from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church and Churchmen. The remouing of the bowndſtone hurtes but a fewe, and to their little loſſe. The taking away of the maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the Miniſter hurts a great number, and keepes from them learned and godly men, which ſhoulde teach and gouerne them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If Ieſus</hi> Chriſt did caſt out of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all them that ſold &amp; bought in the temple,<note place="margin">Math. chap. <hi>21.</hi> ver. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and did ouerthrowe the tables of the mony chaungers, and the ſeates of them that ſold doues, hee will deale more rowndly with buyers and ſeſlers of Cleargy liuinges, becauſe their ſinne is greater. They which ſold doues and were mony changers in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem had two goodly pretenſes for their marchandize: firſt that the people
<pb facs="tcp:23978:8"/>which came to ſacrifice at Ieruſalem needed not to ſeeke farre for doues to ſacrifice, or for monie to offer in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, becauſe they might haue both mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; doues at hand for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeruice of God in Ieruſalem. Secondly, the exchange of monie and ſale of doues was not in the ſanctuarye but in the court of the Temple, which court was ſometimes tearmed by the name of the temple. They which make marchandize of cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy liuings haue no ſuch colour for their defence, they cannot ſay that they are monie chaungers and doue ſellers, to furniſh Gods people with monie for offeringes and with doues for ſacrifice: but they take mony and gifts of corrupt men, to famiſh Gods people and to keep from them the goodlye funneſhyne of Gods fauour, which the ſounde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell doth very liuely &amp; comfortably offer vnto them. They which ſold doues and changed monie in Ieruſalem, defiled not the ſanctuary but the court of the temple: they which ſell Church liuinges doe great hurt to the bodie of the Churche and common<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb facs="tcp:23978:8"/>therefore their condemnation will bee more greauous becauſe their ſinne is greater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Emperour</hi> Conſtantinus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded Anilinus,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. chap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> to bee carefull that gardens, howſes, or any thing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer belonging to the right of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhould with all ſpeede bee reſtored to them. If pulling from the Churches had beene lawfull, Conſtantinus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement had deſerued neither li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king nor performance. Our gracious ſouereigne Queene Elizabethes both deſire and pleaſure is, that worthy men be called for, and haue that maintenance freely which belonges vnto them: this hath her Maieſty deliuered in ſpeeche, and it is prouided for by hir highnes lawes. All y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare God doe thanke him for, and are glad of this, and do therefore think very hardly of corrupt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which will not be reſtrayned and reformed ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Gods and the Queenes both lawes and ſpeech, or by the woorthye example of Conſtantinus, or by the teſtimonye of their owne conſciences, which cannot but both accuſe &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne them,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>They which</hi> preſent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal liuings are called patrons, that is to ſay, defenders of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church: to keepe back either all or part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church liuinges is not to be a ſhielde to couer the Churche and the Miniſter, but a ſworde to cut them, and therefore they may iuſtly be called the ſchollers of <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> the Churchrobber which was ſlaine for his villanies.<note place="margin">2. Machab. chap. 4. ver. 42.</note> If a patrone preferre a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for monye and corruption, hee muſt needs thinke hardly and vily of that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, &amp; the miniſter likewiſe of that patrone: for who can like a miniſter when he feeles his corruption, and what miniſter though hee fiſhe with a ſiluer hooke, wil accompt of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> patrons friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which he payes ſo deare for: and what good men can like of eyther him that preferres or is preferred in this ſorte: will they not iudge them to bee ſtraunge market men? Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoam made Prieſtes of the loweſt of the people which were not of the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of Leui,<note place="margin">1. Kings chap 12. ver. 31. &amp; chap. <hi>13.</hi> ver. 33.</note> but hee did it for monye. For the like reſpect, I feare, manye haue beene preferred, which cannot
<pb facs="tcp:23978:9"/>be allowed for Prophets becauſe they neuer were the ſonnes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I haue handeled</hi> theſe poyntes, I truſt for the good of all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they which are guiltie of this ſinne may make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and leaue the practiſe of it, and that they which are not guiltie of it, may take good heede that they fall not into that ſinke of corruption. If anye be offended with this I haue ſet downe, it is their faulte and not mine: for the ſeed which I haue ſowen is very good, but the ground which receiues it not, is very bad: but my comfort is this, that I haue pleaſed almighty God and his ſeruauntes in this godly labour, though this certayne truthe bee a ſhut booke &amp; as a ſealed letter vnto graceles Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morantes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether landes and penſions gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for the maintenance of Idolatrie, may and ought to be conuerted to the ſeruice of God?</p>
            <p>Anſwere.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:10"/>
            <p>They may &amp; ought: for if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould conuert them to their priuate vſe, it might bee iuſtly thought, that in abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing ſuperſtition priuate gaine is the marke which is louelled at, and not the promoting of Gods true religion. This is Auguſtines iudgement in a notable and learned Epiſtle,<note place="margin">Aug. epiſt. <hi>154<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ad Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licolam.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues to be greatly liked of.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:10"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>SInce the printing of the firſt part of my Catechiſme, I haue bin earneſtly dealt with to write ſomewhat of the Sacraments. The requeſt was verie equall, and I haue yeelded to it, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by theſe Treatiſes. The courſe I haue taken in them is plaine and ſhort: If they ſhall profite ſuch as haue neede of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, I will thanke God very humbly for it, and hereafier, by Gods asſiſtance, ſet downe another ſhort Treatiſe of the Scripture, and the Church and Confesſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for their further benefit. Theſe points are waighty, but neceſſary arguments to be handled, yet very breeſly: becauſe the memories of the ſimple are verie ſhorte and long diſcourſes are not eaſily dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by them. God giue vs grace to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in the knowledge of his truth, and to frame our liues accordingly, to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and our comforte, through Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23978:11"/>
               <list>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Table of ſuch poyntes as are</hi> contained in the firſt part of this Treatiſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> VVHat a Sacrament is.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> There are but two Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, Baptiſme &amp; the Lords ſupper: the other fiue which went vnder the name of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, are no Sacraments.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> It is not in any mans power to make a Sacrament.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> Whether the Sacraments of the olde and new teſtament are all one, and howe they differ.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> The Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts muſt not be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred at all aduentures to euery one.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6</hi> The ſigne muſt not bee confounded with the thing fignified in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7</hi> The Sacraments are not to be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med better for the worthines of the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, or the worſe for his vnworthines.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8</hi> The Sacramentall ſignes offer grace vnto all, but doe not of their owne nature conferre grace vnto all that doe receiue them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9</hi> Why almighty God would haue the external ſignes in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of very ſimple and vſuall things.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:11"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10</hi> The Sacraments are not naked &amp; bare ſignes.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>11</hi> The Sacramentes muſt haue the word of God annexed to them.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>12</hi> Gods Church hath neede of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo long as it is in this world.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>13</hi> The Sacraments are highly to bee eſteemed.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>14</hi> The contempt of the Sacramentes is very daungerous.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>15</hi> The Sacraments during the tyme of the action of Baptiſme &amp; of the Lords ſupper are Sacraments, but after the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ended, they are no Sacraments.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>16</hi> What good we receiue by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:12"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Treatiſe of the <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 What a Sacrament is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> Sacrament is a viſible ſigne of an inuiſible grace.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2 There are but two Sacramentes, Baptiſme and the Lordes Supper: The other fiue which went vnder the name of Sacramentes, that is to ſay, Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, Orders, Pennaunce, Extreme vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Confirmation are no Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SAynt Paule</hi> prouing that the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were equal vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Corinth,<note place="margin">1. Cor. chap. <hi>10.</hi> ver. 2. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> and conſequently of vs in the externall ſignes of Gods fauour, nameth onelye Baptiſme and the Lordes Supper: wherein hee had dealt verie ſtrangely, if of ſeuen Sacramentes he had left out fiue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Two thinges</hi> are eſpecially &amp; ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:23978:12"/>required vnto euery neceſſary Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Churche. Firſt a ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble outward element: Secondly the word of inſtitution: the element in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is water: the elementes in the Lords Supper are bread &amp; wyne: the word of inſtitution in baptiſme, is that which is pronounced by the miniſter: I baptize thee in the name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of the Sonne,<note place="margin">Math. chap. <hi>28.</hi> ver. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> and of the holye Ghoſt. the word of inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſupper, is:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 23.24.25.</note> The Lorde Ieſus the ſame night that he was betrayed tooke bread, and when he had giuen thanks he brake it and ſayde, take, eate, this is my bodie which is broken for you, this do ye in remembrance of me. After the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner alſo he tooke the cup when hee had ſupped, ſaying, this cup is the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament in my blood, this doe as oft as yee drinke it in remembrance of me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Matrimony,</hi> orders, &amp; pennance haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word of God but no outward element. Extreme vnction and Confirmation haue neither word nor element.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection for Matrimony.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For this cauſe ſhall a man leaue father<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Epheſ. chap.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 31.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23978:13"/>and mother and ſhal cleaue to his wife &amp; they twayne ſhall be one fleſh: this is a great myſterie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. as the Church of Rome tranſlateth it, therefore. Matrunonie is a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If by this word (Miſtery) we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>2.</hi> Theſ. chap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. <hi>7.</hi> Ephe chap. <hi>5.</hi> ver. <hi>32.</hi>
                     </note> iniquity ſhal be a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle makes mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Myſtery of iniquitie: Beſides, this My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery pertayneth not to the carnall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of man and wife, but to the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all mariage of Chriſt and the Church: S. Paules wordes doe warrant this: this is (ſaith he) a great ſecret, but I ſpeake concerning. Chriſt and the Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection for Matrimonie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mariage is a ſigne of a holy thing, therefore it is a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The argument folowes not: for if to bee a ſigne of a holie thing bee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to make a Sacrament, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe mariage is a Sacrament becauſe it reſembles the coniunction of Chriſte and his Churche: but by this meanes
<pb facs="tcp:23978:13"/>we are like to haue more then ſeuen ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes: for then Chriſtes waſhing of his diſciples feete, his imbracing of young children in his arme, and almoſt all his actions, becauſe they are ſignes of holy thinges muſt goe for Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection for extreeme vnction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Is any man ſicke among you: let him call for the Elders of the Church,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iam. chap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſe</hi> 14.15.</note> and let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pray for him &amp; anoint him with oyle in the name of the Lorde, and the prayer of fayth ſhall ſaue the ſicke, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him vp. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle ſetteth downe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement in theſe wordes (let him call for the Elders of the Church) and the element in theſe words (anoint him with oyle, and a promiſe aunexed to the element in theſe wordes (and the Lord ſhall rayſe him vp), therefore extreeme vnction is a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I graunt there is a comaundement, an element, and a promiſe, but becauſe that commaundement is not giuen to
<pb facs="tcp:23978:14"/>vs nor that promiſe belongs to vs, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing with oyle which was vſed in the Primitiue Church, muſt not in that caſe be vſed of vs, and therefore ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is nor muſt bee accounted a Sacrament for vs. Circumciſion had the worde of inſtitution and a ſenſible outward element, but becauſe che com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement and promiſe was giuen to the Iſraelites and not to vs, it was a Sacrament to them, but is not ſo to vs. Secondly the Apoſtle Iames ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of an extraordinary gift of healing by anoynting with oyle, as the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Marke reporteth:<note place="margin">Mark. chap. <hi>6.</hi> verſe. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> whiche extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie gift of healing being ceaſed many yeeres paſt, what extreeme folly is it to retayne annoynting with oyle, which was a ſigne of that gift. Thirdly the annointing with oyle vſed in the Primitiue Churche is very vnlike the extreme vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Popiſh Church. Saint Iames woulde haue all ſicke folkes to be anointed: his woordes are playne (is any ſicke &amp;c.) The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes do anoynt them onely which are at deathes dore. Saint Iames promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb facs="tcp:23978:14"/>recouerie of health to the ſicke which were anointed in the Prinitiue Church, which promiſe was according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perfourmed: his woordes are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt (and the Lorde ſhall rayſe him vp): the Papiſts may promiſe recouerie to them who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they anoint, but they are not in caſe to performe it, for they haue not the gift of healing.</p>
                  <p>If they woulde anſwere they haue it, they might bee iuſtly conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of great, both vanitie and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: vanitie, for vaunting of that which all the worlde ſees they haue not, cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for not curing thoſe ſicke men and women whom they ſee to die preſently after their anointing. Laſtly, the anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in S. Iames time and curing of the ſick extraordinarily by that meanes and godly praiers, did make greatly for the confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and increaſe of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the firſt planting of the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Acts. chap. <hi>5.</hi> verſ. <hi>15.</hi> Act. chap. <hi>19</hi> verſe <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> as Peters ſhadowe, and Paules Nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinnes did. The extreme vnction of the Papiſtes neyther cures ſicke men nor increaſes religion, but nouriſhes ſuperſtition and prooues gaynefull to the popiſh prieſtes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:15"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 It is not in any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s power to make a Sacrament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Iſraelites</hi> had two Sacraments,<note place="margin">Gene. cha. <hi>17</hi> verſ. <hi>10.11.</hi> Exod. cha. <hi>12</hi> verſe <hi>3.</hi> Mat. cha. <hi>21</hi> verſe <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note> Circumciſion and the paſſeouer: God himſelf was the authour of them both.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt aſking</hi> the Phariſes whether Iohns Baptiſme were from heauen, doeth giue vs very clearely to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that it was not to be allowed for a ſacrament, vnles it had bin comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of almightie God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> remembring that by one ſpirite we are all baptiſed into one body,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. cha.</hi> 12 <hi>verſe</hi> 13.</note> doth manifeſtly teach vs, that the Sacramentes are not the worke of any man but of the ſpirit of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saint Paule</hi> doth not take vpon him to inſtitute the Lordes Supper in the Church of Corinthe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. cha.</hi> 11 <hi>verſe</hi> 23.</note> but (for the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſuch abuſes as had crept into that holy Sacrament) deliuers that to them which he receiued of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The name</hi> of the Lordes Supper doeth teach vs that Ieſus Chriſte was the authour of it.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Sacrament</hi> can neuer be without promiſe of ſaluation: all men of the worlde can not of them ſelues promiſe any thing to vs of our ſaluation: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they neither can nor ought of them ſelues to inſtitute or erect any Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 Whether the ſacraments of the old and newe Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t are all one, and how they differ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Circumciſion was</hi> to the Iſraelites a Sacrament of regeneration: Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is ſo to vs. By Circumciſion, the Iſraelites were incorporated into gods viſible Church: ſo are we by Baptiſme. Circumciſion was to them a ſigne of Gods couenant: ſo is Baptiſme to vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Paſchall</hi> Lambe was to the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites a ſacrament of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> immaculate Lambe Chriſte Ieſus, by whoſe blood their redemption ſhoulde bée wrought: the bread and wine in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is a Sacrament to vs of Chriſtes body and blood which is giuen and ſhed for vs.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:16"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Iſraelites</hi> did eate the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meate whiche wee doe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 10. <hi>verſe</hi> 2.</note> becauſe there was one and the ſelfe ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of their Sacraments and ours, that is to ſay, the partaking of Ieſus Chriſt vnto life euerlaſting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacramentes</hi> of the Iſraelites (touching the external ſignes) do differ from ours, but theirs &amp; ours are a like if we conſider the thinges ſignified by them: For in their Sacramentes was expreſſed the death of Chriſt which was then to come: in ours is expreſſed the death of Chriſt already paſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The new</hi> Sacraments inſtituted of Chriſt are plainer and clearer then the Sacramentes vnder the Lawe, as the Goſpell is playner and clearer then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lawe, but the thinges ſignified in and by their ſacramentes and ours, are not contayned more in our Sacramentes then in theirs.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 The Sacramentes muſt not bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred at all aduenture to euerie one.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Paſſeouer</hi> was one of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments amongeſt the Iſraelites.<note place="margin">Exod chap. <hi>12.</hi> verſ. <hi>48.</hi>
                     </note> It was not lawefull for any that was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed, to eate of it.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:17"/>
                  <p>It is not lawfull to giue the precious treaſure of Gods worde to them which do contemne it,<note place="margin">Mat. chap. <hi>7.</hi> verſe <hi>6.</hi>
                     </note> therfore it is as vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to giue vnto them the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which are the ſeales of the worde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Philip the</hi> Emperor offered himſelfe to be partaker of the prayers in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke aſſemblie:<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>6.</hi> chap. <hi>34.</hi>
                     </note> the gouernour of that Church refuſed to admit him, vntill by confeſſion of his ſinnes he ſatiſfied the Church, and had ioyned himſelfe to the penitentiaries in the face of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. The Emperor according to his duetie yeelded his obedience moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. If the Emperour was repelled for a time from the publike prayers, it is a cleare caſe that hee ſhoulde not at that time haue bin admitted to the holy Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Emperour</hi> Theodoſius after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had defiled himſelf with ſhedding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood in the citie of Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,<note place="margin">Theod. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cha. <hi>17.</hi> &amp; <hi>18</hi>
                     </note> was not admitted by Ambroſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Mediolanum either to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, or to preſent him ſelfe to the partaking of the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, vntill Theodoſius by a notable
<pb facs="tcp:23978:18"/>confeſſion of his ſinne had ſatiſfied and reconciled himſelfe to the Churche of God.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 The ſigne muſt not be confounded with the thing ſignified in the Sacrifice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For not</hi> eueryone y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> receiueth the ſigne is partaker of the thing ſignified: This is cleare in Simon Magus for Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and in the traytour Iudas for the Lords Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The water</hi> of Baptiſme is one thing, the blood of Chriſt ſignified by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is another thing: The water pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth our bodyes, Chriſtes blood pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth our ſoules: without partaking of Baptiſme (ſo that contempt be abſent) we may be ſaued, without Chriſts blood we can neuer be ſaued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The bread</hi> of the Sacrament is one thing, the body of Chriſt is another, the breade entereth onely into the bodily mouth, Chriſtes fleſhe entreth onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſoule: without eating the bread of the ſacrament (ſo that contempt bee
<pb facs="tcp:23978:18"/>abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) we may be ſaued, without eating of Chriſtes fleſh we can neuer be ſaued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is</hi> a miſerable bondage of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſt. lib. 5. cap. 5.</note> to take the ſignes (in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts) for the thinges ſignified by them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I confeſſe</hi> that the name of the thing ſignified is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſometime to the ſigne.<note place="margin">Gene. cha. 17 verſe. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> Circumciſion is ſayde to bee the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betweene God &amp; Abraham, when notwithſtanding it was not the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant but the ſigne of Gods couenant. The Lambe is called the Lords Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer,<note place="margin">Exod. cha. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> verſe <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> but the Lambe was not the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage it ſelfe (of the Iſraelites out of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt) but remembred vnto them the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of that great deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theirs out of Egypt. The bread in the Lordes Supper, is called the body of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Aug. contra Adimant. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> but it was onely a figure and ſigne of Chriſts body: &amp; yet the worthy receiuer which bringes fayth and repentaunce with him to the Lords Supper, is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker as of the bread and the wine, ſo of the bodye and blood of the Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:19"/>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 The Sacramentes are not to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed better for the worthineſſe of the miniſter, or the woorſe for his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthines.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> him ſelfe baptiſed not, but his diſciples,<note place="margin">Iohn. chap. 4. verſe 2. Iohn chap. 4. ver. <hi>1.</hi> and chap. <hi>3.</hi> verſe 22.</note> and yet the baptiſme miniſtred by the diſciples was Chriſtes Baptiſme. If that be Chriſtes baptiſme which is miniſtred by man, whatſoeuer the miniſter be, baptiſme ſtill remaines to be Chriſtes baptiſme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wee are</hi> baptiſed in the name not of any creature but of the holy Trinitie:<note place="margin">Cypr. de bapt. Chriſti.</note> therefore whether Iudas or Paule doe baptize, Chriſt doth waſh and put away our ſinnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As golde</hi> is gold of whom ſoeuer it be giuen or receiued, ſo is the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alwayes a Sacrament whether it be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vs by good or bad miniſters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacramentes</hi> are Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: mans lewdneſſe can not peruert the nature of Gods ordinance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Anabaptiſtes</hi> in our time doe thinke that baptiſme is defiled by the lewdneſſe of the miniſter. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſtes
<pb facs="tcp:23978:19"/>in Auguſtins time did eſteeme of the worthineſſe of the Sacrament by the worthineſſe of the miniſter. Theſe are groſſe and palpable errours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is</hi> a cleare trueth in diuinitie that the Sacramentes are neyther bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor woorſe for the goodneſſe or the badneſſe of the miniſters, yet vnlearned and lewde miniſters muſt eyther labor to bee better furniſhed with learning and honeſty for the good of the Church, or els be remooued to the leſſe hurte of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 The Sacramentall ſignes offer grace vnto all, but doe not of their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conferre grace vnto all that doe receyue them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Many haue</hi> been partakers of the Sacramentes, which notwithſtanding were very vngracious. Many of the Iewes receiued Circumciſion of the fleſhe without Circumciſion of the heart. Simon Magus receyued Baptiſme but not regeneration: Audas receyued the breade of
<pb facs="tcp:23978:20"/>the ſupper, but not the body of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacramentes</hi> do bring to paſſe that which they doe figure,<note place="margin">Aug. de bapt. paruulo.</note> onely in the elect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We neyther</hi> doe nor may attribute forgiuenes of ſinnes to the externall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement otherwiſe then inſtrumentally. We muſt by no meanes ſay that grace is contayned eſſentially in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as water in a veſſell, or as medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine in a boxe, but the Sacraments are ſaide to containe grace, becauſe they be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſignes of grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is</hi> a certaine trueth that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes doe alwayes retayne their nature.<note place="margin">Tit chap. 3. verſe 5. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. cha. <hi>10</hi> verſe 16.</note> Baptiſme is a lauer of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation. The Lordes Supper is the communion of Chriſtes body &amp; blood, though no ſparke of faith remayned in the world: but we receiue not the grace which is offered by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Sacraments, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we bring fayth to the partaking of the Sacramentes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If any</hi> aſke me, why the infantes of the faithfull which haue not fayth are preſented to baptiſme, I anſwere that
<pb facs="tcp:23978:20"/>though they haue not fayth, yet they are vnder Gods couenant, wherof Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is to vs a ſure warrant and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Church is clenſed by the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water through the worde,<note place="margin">Ephe chap. 2. verſe 26.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſme doth conferre ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle ioynes together the worde of life and the waſhing of water, as if he ſhoulde ſay, by the Goſpell the meſſage of our waſhing and ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is deliuered vnto vs, and by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, the ſame meſſage is ſealed vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 Why almightie God woulde haue the externall ſignes in the Sacraments to conſiſte of very ſimple and vſuall thinges.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Almightie God</hi> woulde haue them conſiſt of moſt ſimple and vſual things, Firſt that we ſhoulde not hang vpon or
<pb facs="tcp:23978:21"/>cleaue vnto theſe earthly thinges, but lift vp our heartes vnto the Lorde: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, leaſt we which incline to much by our corrupt nature to ſuperſtition, ſhoulde abuſe the outward ſignes. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe hee woulde barre none, no not the pooreſt from beeing partakers of the holy Sacramentes. This courſe did the Lord take in the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iawe: they whiche were not able to offer vnto him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leuit. chap.</hi> 5. <hi>verſ.</hi> 7.11.</note> Oxen, Sheepe, Lambes, &amp;c. did of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vnto him Pigions &amp; turtle Doues. If their abilitie ſerued not for theſe, they offred a little meale.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The outwarde</hi> ſignes in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are very meane and baſe things if wee looke on them with the eyes of our fleſhe, but they are moſt precious and ſinguler Iewelles if wee looke on them with the eyes of our fayth, and do eſteeme them according to the Lordes inſtitution.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 The Sacramentes are not naked and bare ſignes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Baptiſme,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> efficacie of Gods ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, is preſent to waſhe and regenerate
<pb facs="tcp:23978:21"/>thoſe, which appertayne vnto God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lordes</hi> Supper is a ſpirituall banquet,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 3.4.16</note> wherein Gods children are truely and in deede fedde with the body and blood of Chriſt. The apoſtle calleth the Sacrament ſpirituall meate and ſpirituall drinke, and a litle after in the ſame chapter, hee calleth the cuppe of bleſſing which we bleſſe, the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the blood of Chriſte, and the bread which we break, the communion of the body of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacraments</hi> are not bare ſignes, becauſe we haue the Lords inſtitution: they are ſeales of righteouſnes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of grace, they are ſure warrantes of Gods promiſes, whereby God bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe vnto vs and wee likewiſe ſtande bounde to his Maieſtie, ſo that God is our God and we are his people.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 The Sacramentes muſt haue the worde of God annexed to them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For the</hi> worde of inſtitution is the life of the Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacraments</hi> are ſeales of Gods word.<note place="margin">Rom. chap. <hi>4.</hi> verſe <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> Therefore where the word of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution
<pb facs="tcp:23978:22"/>is not, there is no place left to the Sacraments. There is no vſe of that ſeale, and in deede it deſerues not the name of a ſeale, whiche is put to an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written either paper or parchment.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Take away</hi> the word (of inſtitution) and what is the water (of Baptiſme) but water.<note place="margin">Aug. Tract. <hi>80.</hi> in Iohan.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The woorde of inſtitution is added to the element &amp; it becomes a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Gods Churche hath neede of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, ſo long as it is in the worlde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The fayth</hi> of Gods children is true, that is to ſay not counterfaite, but their faith is not perfit in this life. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are pillers of our faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saint Paul</hi> hath theſe wordes: as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as ye ſhall eate this bread and drink this cup,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor cha.</hi> 11 <hi>verſe</hi> 26.</note> ye ſhewe the Lordes death till he come: whereby it is manifeſt, that vntill Chriſtes ſeconde comming, wee haue both neede and vſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, whereof wee ſhall haue neither vſe nor neede in the life to come.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:22"/>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13 The Sacramentes are higly to be eſteemed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacramentes</hi> are pillers of our fayth: they are glaſſes wherein we may beholde the riches of Gods grace which he reacheth vnto vs, they are the Lordes couenauntes: therefore they contayne promiſes, whereby our conſciences are lifted vp to the hope of eternall life. <hi>Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> receiue great benefit by baptiſme,<note place="margin">Galath. chap. 3. ver. 27. 1. Cor. chap. 10. ver. 16.</note> for all that are baptized into Chriſt haue put on Chriſt: &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſupper, bicauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread which we breake is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the bodie of Chriſt, and the cup of bleſſing is the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the bloud of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the Sacramentes</hi> are highly to be eſteemed, what ſhall we thinke of Pope Iohn the <hi>23.</hi> for baptizing and beeing godfather to the great bell of Laterane in Rome, &amp; of the popiſh ſort for giuing out y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue nothing but bare bread &amp; bare wyne in the holy communion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacramentes</hi> are highly to bee accounted of, and honoured as holy my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, but they muſt not bee honoured with diuine honour.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:23"/>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14 The contempt of the Sacraments is very daungerous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The contempt</hi> of Circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which was one of Gods ſacraments was gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly puniſhed.<note place="margin">Gen. chap. 17 ver. 14. Exod. chap. 4. ver. 25.</note> The Angell woulde haue killed Moſes, becauſe his ſonne was not circumciſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Negligence</hi> in keeping the paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,<note place="margin">Nomb. chap. 9. ver. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> was greeuouſly puniſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is a common</hi> &amp; a very ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpeech, that not the want, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme bringeth condemnation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Meſſalian</hi> heretikes did conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, both externall ſignes &amp; Sacraments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Iſraelites were not circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed in the wildernes by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of <hi>40.</hi> yeeres.<note place="margin">Ioſue chap. <hi>5.</hi> ver. 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>God commaunded the Iſraelites to goe on continually in their iourney. If they had beene circumciſed, they had not bin able by reaſon of the ſorenes of their bodies,<note place="margin">Ioſue. chap. 5. ver. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> to do as God commanded them: ſo that Gods latter commaundement, was a diſpenſation to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and deferring of circumciſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:23"/>
                  <p>The Apoſtles would not preſſe the Gentiles to be circumciſed.<note place="margin">Acts. chap. 15 ver. 24.28.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Circumciſion after Chriſtes aſcenſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not a neceſſary Sacrament, but a thing indifferent, that is to ſay, which might for a time eyther be vſed or omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. If it had been a neceſſary ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in the Primitiue Church, Titus ſhould haue beene circumciſed,<note place="margin">Gala. chap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. 3.</note> as Timothie was. Beſides, circumciſion after Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes aſcenſion might not be thruſt vppon the Gentiles,<note place="margin">Acts. chap. <hi>16.</hi> ver. 3.</note> becauſe Moſes muſt giue place to Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15 The Sacraments, during the time of the action of Baptiſme and of the Lordes Supper, are Sacramentes, but after the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is ended, they are no Sacramentes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The elements</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament, during the time of the action which they ſerue for, are true ſignes and pledges of the things ſignified by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for in baptiſme, Chriſtes bloud is propounded to vs as a lauer: with which bloud we being waſhed, are more and more graft into
<pb facs="tcp:23978:24"/>Chriſt, &amp; buried together with Chriſt: In the Lords ſupper, Chriſtes body and bloud is giuen to vs,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Cor. chap. 10. ver. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> and that by diſtinct and ſeueral ſignes (I meane the bread &amp; the wine) as our true meate and true drinke vnto life euerlaſting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When the action</hi> of baptiſme &amp; the Lords ſupper is ended, the water in the font is no Sacrament, but ſimple and common water, and the bread and wine in the Lordes ſupper, are not the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Chriſtes body &amp; bloud, but commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bread and commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wine: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their fault is great, which (after the action of the Sacrament is ended) ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reſerue any part of the elementes for Sacramentes, or doe thinke that a mowſe, dogge, or ſuch like, taſting or eating of the bread (after the Lords ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is ended) doe receiue the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: whereas it is a certaine truth, that if eyther mowſe or dogge ſhoulde eate of the bread in the Lordes Supper, during the time of the holy action, they neyther doe receiue, nor can be ſaide to receiue the Sacrament at any hande. For, ſeeing the Sacraments are ſeales
<pb facs="tcp:23978:24"/>of Gods promiſes, touching eternall life, it is certayne that no ſuch ſeale is or can be giuen vnto, or receiued by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to whom Gods promiſe of eternal life in no wiſe doth appertayne.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16 What good we receiue by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We are put</hi> in mynde by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſtes ineſtimable benefits, which by the lauer of water purgeth vs in baptiſme, and by his fleſh feedeth, and by his blood refreſheth our ſoules in the Lordes ſupper: Our faith is confirmed and increaſed by the Sacraments: we are by them ſtirred vp, to performe great duetie &amp; thankfulneſſe to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God: we are ſeuered by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (as by a partition wall) from all ſuch, as are not entred into the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtianity, &amp; we are by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments more ſurely lincked togither amongeſt our felues.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23978:25"/>
               <list>
                  <head>A table of ſuch poynts as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the ſecond part of this Treatiſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> VVHat Baptiſme is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2</hi> The Baptiſme of infants is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lawfull.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> It is not lawful for women or priuate men to baptize, for only the miniſter muſt doe it.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4</hi> All that dye before Baptiſme are not da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, becauſe we are Chriſtians before we are baptized.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>5</hi> Baptiſme muſt not be deferred to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> long.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>6</hi> Baptiſme muſt not be iterated, that is to ſay, they which are once baptiſed, muſt not be baptized againe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>7</hi> Whether thoſe children which are knowen to be baſe borne, are to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Baptiſme.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>8</hi> What time is fitt for the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſme.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>9</hi> What is required of them which are already baptiſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are of yeares.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:25"/>
                  <head>A Treatiſe of Baptiſme.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 What Baptiſme is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>BAptiſme, is a ſacrament of regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſting of water &amp; the ſpirite by the word of God, whereby wee haue forgiuenes of ſinnes &amp; euerlaſting life according to Chriſtes promiſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2 The Baptiſme of Infantes is verie lawful.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Infants</hi> of the Iſraelites were circumciſed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were eight dayes old:<note place="margin">Gen. chap. <hi>17</hi> ver. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; cha. <hi>21.</hi> ver. <hi>4</hi>
                     </note> our baptiſme is come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of their circumciſion. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that wee are not tyed to the eight day for the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of our infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites were for the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſing of theirs: neither are women children to be barred from bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme amongſt vs, becauſe their women children were not circumciſed: &amp; yet their women children were partakers of Gods promiſe: for vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mankinde all were conſecrated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The children</hi> of the faithfull are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">1. Cor. chap. <hi>7.</hi> ver. <hi>14.</hi> Acts. chap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. 39.</note> they are vnder Gods couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (which couenant is contayned in theſe wordes,
<pb facs="tcp:23978:26"/>I will be thy God and the God of thy ſeede) therefore they may not be barred from baptiſme which is a ſeale of Gods couenant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>He that ſhal beleeue and be baptized, ſhal be ſaued:<note place="margin">Marke. chap. <hi>16.</hi> ver. <hi>16.</hi>
                     </note> therefore none are to bee admitted to baptiſme before they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue: which infantes doe not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſpeaketh onely of thoſe which are capable of his doctrine and which were before alients from his Churche. Such neyther were nor may be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or admitted to baptiſme before they beleeue in Chriſt Ieſus. This is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in the Samaritanes, and the noble man of Ethiopia,<note place="margin">Acts. chap. 8. ver. 12.37.38. &amp; chap. 16. ver. 32.33.</note> and in the Iayler of Philippos, and in a Iewe baptized of late yeeres in London: all which were taught and beleeued in Chriſt, before they were admitted to baptiſme: ſo that Chriſts words doe no more barre Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian infantes from baptiſme, becauſe they beleeue not,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ. chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 10.</note> then Paules doe from meate becauſe they cannot labour.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:26"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3 It is not lawful for women or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate men to Baptiſe, for onely the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter muſt doe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>No man may</hi> take honour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe but hee which is called as Aaron was:<note place="margin">Heb. chap. <hi>5.</hi> ver. 4.</note> to adminiſter eyther the word or ſacrament, is a ſinguler honour in the churche of God: therefore &amp;c. If aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere be made that baptiſme is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I graunt it to be true, when it may bee adminiſtred according to the order which God hath appoynted. Gods order is that a publike miniſter ſhall doe it. Saul had great reaſons in mans iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his ſacrificing in Samuels abſence,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam. chap.</hi> 13. <hi>ver.</hi> 11. 2. <hi>Sam. chap.</hi> 6. <hi>ver.</hi> 6.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and Vzzah from ſtaying the Arke which was otherwiſe like to haue fallen: but becauſe they tooke vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that, wherevnto God had not called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they receiued a iuſt rewarde of their raſhnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Sacramentes</hi> are ſeales of the worde:<note place="margin">Math. chap. <hi>28.</hi> ver. <hi>19.</hi>
                     </note> our ſauiour Chriſt ioyned them togither, when hee ſent foorth his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and preſcribed a forme of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme in theſe wordes, goe and teach all nations, baptizing them in the name of
<pb facs="tcp:23978:27"/>the father and the ſonne and the holye Ghoſt. The ſelfe ſame men are authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by Chriſt to baptize, which are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized to preach, I meane y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Apoſtles, whom the publique miniſter ſucceedes in preaching the word &amp; adminiſtring the Sacraments. This difference, is notwithſtanding betwene the Apoſtles and vs: they were called immediately by Chriſt himſelfe, ſo are not we: they had Gods giftes miraculouſly pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon them, ſo haue not we: they had all the world for their plough lande, ſo haue not we: ſeing the Apoſtleſhip was long agoe at an end. If the Apoſtleſhip be ended, what ſo much as colour of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge hath the Pope for erecting a new Apoſtleſhip, and ſending heardes of ſuſperſtitious Ieſuites and droues of Maſſing prieſtes into this realme of England. I will ſay nothing of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion deliuered by theſe new Apoſtles, becauſe their Apoſtleſhip and doctrine haue not Chriſtes but the Popes hande and ſeale to confirme them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Phariſies</hi> did thinke it vnlawful,
<pb facs="tcp:23978:27"/>and that iuſtly, that any one without cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſhould adminiſter baptiſme: their wordes to Iohn Baptiſt, are manifeſt.<note place="margin">Iohn. chap. <hi>1.</hi> ver. <hi>25.</hi>
                     </note> If thou art not Chriſt nor Elias &amp;c. why doeſt thou baptize: as if they ſhould ſay vnto Iohn, thou art not a publique miniſter, therefore thou mayeſt not bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize. The Phariſees deſerue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for not allowing a priuate man to baptize, but they were fowly deceiued in taking Iohn Baptiſt to bee a priuate man, for Iohn Baptiſt was that Elias which the Prophet Malachie &amp; our Sauiour Chriſt ſpake of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no priuate man as the Phariſees i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The adminiſtration</hi> of baptiſme by women,<note place="margin">Epiph. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cont. haereſ. Tertul. de preſcript. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. haeret.</note> is a braunche of Marcious he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and is condemned by Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us and Tertullian.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To ſay that</hi> eyther a midwife or a lay man, as we call him, may adminiſter the Sacrament, becauſe the miniſter is not then in place, is as if we ſhould allowe a priuate man to condemne a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer. becauſe the magiſtrate is not
<pb facs="tcp:23978:28"/>then at hand to doe it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sephora,<note place="margin">Exod. chap. 4. ver. 25.</note> Moſes wife did circumciſe hir ſonne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sephoraes fact was vnorderly and confuſed,<note place="margin">Exod chap. <hi>4.</hi> ver. 25.26.</note> for ſhee did it, firſt, in a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and angry fit, as appeareth in the text: ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, in the preſence of Moſes, which is ſufficient to improue her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, euen by the Papiſts iudgement, which thinke it vnlawfull for a woman to baptize, when any man is in place.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 All that dye before baptiſme are not damned, becauſe wee are Chriſtians before we are baptized.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abraham was</hi> iuſtified before he was circumciſed:<note place="margin">Rom. chap. 4. ver. <hi>11.</hi> Acts. chap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. 38.39.</note> otherwiſe circumciſion coulde not haue beene called by Saynt Paule a ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gods promiſe</hi> belongs to Chriſtian Infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts before their baptiſme (otherwiſe baptiſme which is a ſeale of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe ſhould be denied the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>): therfore they are children of the promiſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:23978:28"/>Chriſtians before they are baptized.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Infantes</hi> dying before baptiſme are da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, two groſſe abſurdities would folow: firſt the ſaluation of our infants, ſhould reſt not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which is the ground worke of our ſaluation, but vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeale which is put to the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant: ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, the ſaluation and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of infants ſhould conſiſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence &amp; negligence of their parents &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptiſme was</hi> miniſtred in Theſſalia only on Eaſter day,<note place="margin">Socrat. lib. 5. cap. <hi>22.</hi> Tertul. de Baptiſ.</note> and in Carthage in Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s time only at Eaſter &amp; Whit ſontide. If the infantes of the faithfull be not Chriſtians before their baptiſme, what ſhal we ſay of the infants of Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalia and Carthage, which dyed before Eaſter.</p>
                  <p>The Papiſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize one of yeeres, aſke theſe queſtions of him before his baptiſme: doeſt thou beleeue, doeſt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enounce the Deuil? the party anſweres, I beleue, I renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the deuill: whereby it is cleere, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee ey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther is indeed, or at the leaſt is eſteemed of them to bee a Chriſtian before hee is baptized, &amp; ſo conſequently admitted by
<pb facs="tcp:23978:29"/>them to the partaking of that ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plaine men</hi> of the countrie, doe marke onely thoſe ſheepe for their own, which they eyther knowe or at the leaſt doe take to be their owne. Baptiſme is one of Gods ſeales: The church doth onely marke thoſe with this ſeale, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they eyther know, or at the leaſt do take before the adminiſtration of baptiſme, to be Gods la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes &amp; ſheepe. If they which are offered to baptiſme, are Gods ſheepe &amp; lambes before their baptiſme: it is a cleere caſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are Chriſtians before they are baptized, &amp; conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is not the cauſe but a ſeake of our coniunction with almighty God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The vncircumciſed man childe in whoſe fleſh,<note place="margin">Gen. chap. 17 ver. 14</note> the foreſkinne is not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, euen that perſon ſhall bee cut off, from his people, becauſe he hath bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my couenant.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If any of the Iſraelites were ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther principalles or acceſſaries to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting of their own circumciſion, they deſerued to be cut off, otherwiſe not, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:23978:29"/>we will condemne the child for the fault of his Pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which is barbarous crueltie. The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Hebrewes, if they dyed the fifth or ſixth day after their birth, were not vnder conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Gen. chap. <hi>17.</hi> ver. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> for the eight day was the day of circumciſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Except a man be borne of water &amp; of the ſpirit,<note place="margin">Iohn. chap. <hi>3.</hi> ver. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> he cannot enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If we vnderſtand this of baptiſme, what ſhal we ſay of the Emperour Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinian which went to Ambroſe the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Medtolanum to be baptized, and was ſlayne in his iourney before hee came to Ambroſe: ſhall we condemne him for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baptiſme, becauſe Chriſt ſayde to Nichodemus except a man be borne &amp;c? This dealing were very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory. If aunſwere bee made, that Valentinians deſire of Baptiſme is a ſufficient defence, I graunt it was ſo: and, if the Emperours deſire keepe him out of the compaſſe of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, why maye not Gods promiſe be ſufficient to deliuer the infantes of
<pb facs="tcp:23978:30"/>the faithfull from condemnation if they dye vnbaptized: for not the want but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Baptiſme doth condemne vs. Beſides, our Sauiour Chriſtes ſpeeche was with Nicodemus, which was of good yeeres, and might haue at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the vſe both of water &amp; a miniſter for this godly purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the Infantes of Chriſtians be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Gods couenant before they be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, their Baptiſme ſeemes to be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous: why are they baptized:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Gods commaundement muſt be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled. He commaunded both circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; baptiſme, &amp; puniſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſharply in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites, &amp; will puniſh the contempt of baptiſme gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly in vs. Beſides, Gods promiſe which pertayneth to our infantes,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts. chap.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 38.39.</note> muſt be confirmed with the outward ſeale of Baptiſme, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we may be alwayes mynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of Gods promiſe. Laſtly, the godly praiers of the miniſter &amp; of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the child to baptiſme, do greatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit the infant, and the congregation
<pb facs="tcp:23978:30"/>which is then preſent at the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of baptiſme, receiues ſome inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion touching their ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 Baptiſme muſt not be deferred too long.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptiſme is</hi> a Sacrament of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation: by Baptiſme we enter and are graft into Gods viſible Church: Gods couenant with vs and our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren is ſealed by Baptiſme, both in vs and our children. Therefore &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptiſme contayneth</hi> in it the firſt profeſſion of Chriſtian religion: If it be deferred too long, when it may bee godly come by, it draweth the parentes and friendes of the infant into ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either of Atheiſme or Anabaptiſme, and beſides, breedeth great offence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gregorie Nazianzene</hi> was a By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſonne:<note place="margin">Orat. in ſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. baptiſ.</note> he was not baptiſed before he was of good yeeres: it was a groſſe fault in that time, and Nazianzene him ſelfe inueigheth ſharply againſt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of Baptiſme.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nectarius was</hi> appointed Biſhop of<note place="margin">Sozo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. li. cap. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23978:31"/>Conſtantinople before hee was bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. Nectarius was a good man, but this deferring of baptiſme commendes neyther him nor the Biſhops of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſtantinus deferred</hi> his baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vntill his dying day.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 4. de vita Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantini.</note> He was a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Emperour, but this fact of his, can not be iuſtified.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What if by reaſon of differring of baptiſme, the infant die vnbaptiſed?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a groſſe faulte in the childes friendes, &amp; muſt be puniſhed with great ſeueritie: but the infant deſerues no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation for this at Gods hands, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhutting from Chriſtian buriall at the Churches handes: for not the want but contempt of baptiſme doth conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vs.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6 Baptiſme muſt not be iterated, that is to ſay, they whiche are once baptized muſt not be baptized againe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Chr. chap. <hi>30.</hi> verſe 9. &amp; chap. <hi>35.</hi> verſe <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Iſraelites</hi> which reuolted from Gods religion in the raigne of Ezechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb facs="tcp:23978:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>and Ioſias, were not circumciſed the ſeconde time: onely, they teſtified their vnfaygned repentance and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the Lorde by celebration of the Paſſeouer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Baptiſme is</hi> a Sacrament of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, regeneration is the miſterie of this Sacrament: the miſterie of this Sacrament cannot be iterated (becauſe they which are altogether fallen from grace cannot be renewed):<note place="margin">Heb. chap. 6. verſe 4.5.6.</note> Therefore the Sacrament of regeneration may not be iterated.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They which</hi> are baptized eyther of popiſhe or other heretiques (which in their baptiſme do adde to the element the word of inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) are not baptized into the name of any creature but of the holy Trinitie: thefore they haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued true baptiſme (as touching the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of baptiſme) and conſequently not mans but Gods baptiſme: and therefore neede not any ſeconde baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. If it were Gods baptiſme, it contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it, promiſe of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, mortification of the fleſhe,
<pb facs="tcp:23978:32"/>quickening of the ſpirit, and partaking of Chriſt. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seeing that wee ſinne dayly, and that our ſinnes are done away by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, why ſhoulde wee not deſire, and preſent our ſelues to be very often bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the efficacie of Baptiſme did reach only to the ſinnes committed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Baptiſme, as for example, in yong children, to origmall ſinne, and in thoſe w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> are of yeeres, both to their original and actuall ſinnes, which went before their baptiſme: I coulde like well of them whiche for the cleare waſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of their ſins eyther deferred their Baptiſme vnto their dying day, which was groſſe ignoraunce, or of ſuch whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in our time for the like reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would deſire to be often Baptiſed, whiche is a palpable errour. It is a certaine trueth
<pb facs="tcp:23978:32"/>in diuinitie, that our ſinnes committed after Baptiſme do not aboliſh our bap, tiſme: For Chriſtes puritie is offered to vs in Baptiſme: whiche puritie of Chriſt, becauſe it is alwayes in force, is not raſed out by any ſinnes of ours, but clenſeth vs from all filthines whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. The Galathians reuolted from that truth which Paul had taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.<hi>5.6.</hi> chap.</note> and were corrupt in their liues: theſe were great ſinnes after they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Baptiſme: Paul notwithſtanding reuiueth their faith by that Baptiſme which, before, they had receiued.<note place="margin">Gal. chap. <hi>3.</hi> verſe. <hi>27.</hi>
                     </note> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme muſt not be ſhut vp in ſtraighter rome then Chriſt himſelfe, ſeeing that in Baptiſme we put on Chriſt:<note place="margin">Rom. chap. 6. verſ. <hi>1.2.3.</hi>
                     </note> and the efficacie of Baptiſme, is not leſſe then the efficacie of Chriſtes death, vnto whiche Baptiſme hath a ſingular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To be</hi> once regenerate and to haue once entred into Chriſts Church is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, neyther is any of Gods electe caſt out at any time: for he that is once indewed with the ſpirit of ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is alwayes endewed with the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:23978:33"/>ſpirite of ſanctification. My reaſons are theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The giftes</hi> and calling of God,<note place="margin">Rom. chap. <hi>11</hi> verſe 29. 1. Pet. chap. <hi>1</hi> verſe 23.</note> are without repentance.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The worde</hi> of God whereby we are regenerate, is immortall ſeede, that is to ſay, neuer dieth in his children. The ſhielde of fayth may be wounded, but it can not be ſtricken through.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whoſoeuer is</hi> borne of God ſinneth not,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. chap. 3 verſe. 9. &amp; cap. 5. ver. <hi>18</hi>
                     </note> for his ſeed remayneth in him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can he ſinne, becauſe he is borne of God. The Apoſtle Iohn meaneth not that ſinne dwelleth not in Gods chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but that it hath not dominion ouer them: and therefore Paul ſaith not, let not ſinne dwel,<note place="margin">Rom. chap. 6. verſe 12. 2. Sam chap. 11. verſe. 4.15.<hi>24.</hi> 2. Sam. chap. <hi>12.</hi> verſ. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </note> but let not ſinne raigne in your mortall bodies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dauid dealt</hi> verye ſtrangely with Vrias and with the Lordes armie: his faith ſeemed to be quenched, but he was not cleane ſpoyled of all ſparkes of grace: there remayned as it were, a quicke coale in the aſhes: other wiſe the Prophet Nathan had not ſo eaſily and ſpeedily awaked him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſtes reſurrection</hi> is a notable
<pb facs="tcp:23978:33"/>piller of our faith, and the very locke and kepe of all religion.<note place="margin">Iohn chap. 20. verſe. 25.</note> The Apoſtle Thomas doubted ſo much of it, that he vttered theſe wordes: except I ſee in his handes the print of the nayles, and put my finger into the printe of the nayles, and put my hande into his ſide, I will not beleeue it. This ſinne of Thomas was ſo groſſe, that it might he fealt with the fingers, and yet faith was not cleane extinguiſhed in him,<note place="margin">Iohn chap. 20 verſe <hi>28.</hi>
                     </note> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his anſwere to Chriſte, my Lord and my God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They whiche</hi> thinke that they are vtterly voyde of Gods ſpirite in whom the fruites of the ſpirit do not alwaies appeare, are like vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which thinke there is no ſire where there is no flame, and that trees are dead in winter, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they bring forth neyther fruit nor leaues in winter.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 Whether thoſe children whiche are knowen to be baſe borne are to bee admitted to baptiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:34"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The children</hi> which are baſe borne amongſt vs, are not to bee ſhutte from baptiſme for the parentes ſinne, if ſuch as feare God preſent them to baptiſme, and promiſe faithfullye to ſee them brought vp in the feare of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> had a baſe ſonne, but hee was baptiſed,<note place="margin">Aug. confeſ. lib. 9. cap. 6.</note> and verye Chriſtianly brought vp.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 What time is fitte for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of baptiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Circumciſion was</hi> adminiſtred the eyght day after the childs birth:<note place="margin">Gene. cha. <hi>17.</hi> verſe 12. &amp; chap. <hi>21.</hi> verſe 4. Luk. chap. <hi>1.</hi> verſ. 59. &amp; cha. 2. ve. <hi>21</hi>
                     </note> at that time Iſaac, Iohn Baptiſt, and Ieſus Chriſt, were circumciſed. If the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both was the eyght day after the childs birth, hee was circumciſed on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both day. <hi>Iohn chap.</hi> 7. <hi>verſe</hi> 23.</p>
                  <p>That tyme is fitteſt for the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Baptiſme, wherein care is had that the infants die not vnbaptiſed, if it may bee done without breache of Gods order, and yet, that their ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which tie ſaluation to baptiſme, at no hande be fauoured. The Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:23978:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>day is a very fit day for Baptiſme, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the preſence of the congregation.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 What is required of them whiche are alreadie baptized when they are of yeeres.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is required, firſt, that they beleeue aright: ſecondlye, that they mortifie the bodie of ſinne: Laſtly, that they walke in newneſſe of life: a principall branch whereof, is, to be at vnitie with the godly. One God is father of all,<note place="margin">Ephe. chap. 4 verſe <hi>4.5.6.</hi>
                     </note> one Chriſt hath redeemed vs all, one holye ghoſt doth ſanctifie vs all, one fayth and one baptiſme is common to vs all, &amp; there is but one hope of our calling, I meane, euerlaſting life: therefore it becomes vs to bee linked together in the feare of God. Salomon ſayth, that a threefolde corde can not eaſely be broken:<note place="margin">Eccle. chap. 4 verſe. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> if this ſixefolde and golden chaine will not holde vs, wee breake it not by the power of God,<note place="margin">Iudg. cha. 16. verſe 9.</note> as Sampſon did his cordes, but by ſome other power which is not of God. Many grapes make one cuppe of wine, many cornes
<pb facs="tcp:23978:35"/>one loafe of bread, wee are members of one body, whereof Chriſt is the heade: therefore we muſt be at vnitie with Chriſt, by giuing great honour to him, and with our fellow members by doyng good vnto them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23978:35"/>
               <list>
                  <head>A table of ſuch poynts as are contayned in the laſt part of this treatiſe.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1</hi> WHat the Lordes Supper is.</item>
                  <item>2 Why two eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, that is to ſay, bread &amp; wine, are vſed in the Lordes ſupper &amp; but one eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is to ſay, water, in the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baptiſme.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3</hi> Why Chriſt did celebrate the Supper at night.</item>
                  <item>4 The eſſentiall partes of the Lordes Supper are not to be omitted, but the accidentall may.</item>
                  <item>5 None may preſume to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the Lords Supper, but after dewe examination of themſelues.</item>
                  <item>6 The godly are not defiled, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion at ſuch time, as wicked men do preſent them ſelues, and are admitted to the Lords table.</item>
                  <item>7 The Lordes Supper muſt be commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all the godly, not priuate to the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter alone.</item>
                  <item>8 Gods people muſt not be barred from the cup in the Lordes Supper.</item>
                  <item>9 What conſecration is.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>10</hi> The ſubſtance of bread and wine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
<pb facs="tcp:23978:36"/>in the Lords Supper, after the wordes of conſecration.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>11</hi> The wicked do not eate Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in the Sacrament.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>12</hi> Chriſtes body, is not euery where.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>13</hi> The bread and wine in the Lordes Supper, muſt not bee reſerued for any ſuperſtitious vſe.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>14</hi> Howe gods children muſt be haue themſelues, at and after, the recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the holy Supper.</item>
               </list>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A Treatiſe of the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1 What the Lordes Supper is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Lordes Supper is a holy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein according to Chriſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, the Sacrament of his bodye and blood, by a miſticall breaking of breade and bleſſing of the cuppe, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed by the miniſter and receyued by the godly aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blie, &amp; wherein the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Chriſtes ſacrifice on the alter of the croſſe, is celebrated with perfourmance of moſt humble thankes to his Maieſtie, and of Chriſtian chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie amongſt our ſelues.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2 Why two elements, that is to ſay, bread and wine are vſed in the Lordes Supper and but one element, that is to ſay, water, in the Sacrament of Baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt in</hi> baptiſme is propounded vnto vs as a lauer, therefore only water
<pb facs="tcp:23978:37"/>is ſufficient. But in the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, becauſe Chriſt (as heauenly foodé) is giuen vnto vs, and that this life of ours, hath neede as well of drinke as meate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it pleaſed our Sauiour Chriſt to vſe in this holy ſupper, both wine and bread, that we may be well aſſured, that our whole life is to bee ſought by vs in Ieſus Chriſt alone.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Paſſeouer</hi> conſiſted of two ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, meate and drinke.<note place="margin">Exod. cha. 12 verſe <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> The lambe with the vnleauened breade was the meate, the cup of the Teſtament wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there was remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the blood, whiche was clapt vppon the Iſraelites doore poſtes, for aſſurance of their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraunce our of Egypt) was the drinke in the Paſſeouer. The Lordes ſupper conſiſteth of two partes, meat &amp; drinke. Chriſtes body offred for vs on the croſſe is the meate: Chriſtes blood ſhedde on the croſſe for our ſinnes, is the drynke: Our Sauiour Chriſt inſtituting a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of this meate and drinke,<note place="margin">Matth. chap. 26. vs. 26.<hi>27</hi>
                     </note> vſeth bread and wine for the externall ſignes in this Sacrament.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:37"/>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 <hi>Why Chriſt did celebrate the ſupper at night.</hi>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Paſſeouer by Moſes law was to be eaten at night:<note place="margin">Exod. cha. <hi>12</hi> verſe. 8. Ioſu. chap. 5. verſ. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> Chriſt did firſt eate the Paſchall lambe, and did preſently after, inſtitute the Sacramente of the Supper in the place of the Paſſeouer. Wee are not tyed to the euentide for the celebration of the Lords Supper, becauſe Chriſte did ſo: for wee are not bounde to eate any Paſſeouer, immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly before the Lords ſupper, as Chriſt was by the lawe of Moſes: and in the forenoone, whileſt we are faſting, wee are more earneſtly and reuerently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to the partaking of the word and Sacrament. He that thinkes that the Lordes Supper muſt of force be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred at night, becauſe Ieſus Chriſt did ſo, will, I feare, bee mooued by a little perſwaſion, to deferre baptiſme vntill the age of thirtie yeeres,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> becauſe Chriſt before that time was not partaker of that holy Sacrament.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:38"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4 The eſſentiall partes of the Lords Supper are not to be omitted, but the accidentall may.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The eſſentiall</hi> ceremonies of the Lordes ſupper are theſe: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the miniſter after a reuerent deliuery of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> words of Chriſtes inſtitution, and inuocation of the name of God, breaketh the bread: &amp; when it is broken, diſtributeth it to the communicants in order, &amp; afterwards, likewiſe the cup. They whiche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them ſelues to the Lordes table, are commaunded to take and eate the bread, and to drinke of the cuppe, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lordes death, that is to ſay, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing their fayth in Chriſt Ieſus, with a ſolemne remembrance of his paſſion, &amp; humble thankeſgiuing to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, for that ineſtimable benefit. Theſe eſſentiall ceremonies, may not bee ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther altered or omitted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The accidentall</hi> ceremonies of the Lordes Supper, are, that it was mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred at night, &amp; to the diſciples, whileſt they did ſitte at table. Theſe accidentall
<pb facs="tcp:23978:38"/>ceremonies, may bee altred by the Churches ordre.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5 None may preſume to preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the Lordes Supper, but after due examination of themſelues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>None might eate</hi> the Paſſeouer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was prepared.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chro. cha.</hi> 35. <hi>ver.</hi> 6.</note> The Paſſeouer was the ſame to the Iſraelites, that the holie ſupper is to vs: but becauſe our ſacrament is more excellent then theirs, great care muſt be had in prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our ſelues.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saynt Paule</hi> commaundeth a man to examine himſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. chap. <hi>11.</hi> ver. <hi>28.</hi>
                     </note> before the perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the holy Supper. This exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation conſiſts in faith and repentance, faith containeth the truth of our beleef: repentaunce concerneth the amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Weakenes of</hi> faith, ought not to withdraw vs from the holy communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſeeing, it is inſtituted for the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of our faith.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vncleannes</hi> of life, which is priuate and not openly knowen, neyther may
<pb facs="tcp:23978:39"/>nor doth barre any fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but ſuch as meane not to amend.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6, The godly are not defiled if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the holy communion at ſuch time as wicked men doe preſent themſelues and are admitted to the Lordes table.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He</hi> that eateth and drinketh vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, eateth and drinketh iudgement to himſelfe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 21. <hi>ver.</hi> 29.</note> S. Paule ſaieth, to himſelfe not to others.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> willeth a man to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelfe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 21. <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</note> before he preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t himſelfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſupper. Hee requireth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municant to examine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of that church, which, no doubt, he would haue required, if a godly ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were defiled by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnworthines of any lewd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is not lawfull for vs to eate our owne bread with a wicked man: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not lawfull to eate the Lordes bread with him.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 5 <hi>ver.</hi> 11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is in our power to practiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> former, but it is not in our power to abſtayne
<pb facs="tcp:23978:39"/>from the Lords ſupper, though eaſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be, at that time partakers with vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is a great</hi> ſinne for a knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wicked ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either to miniſter y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords ſupper, or to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t himſelf to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; ſuch boldnes muſt be ſeuerely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in whoſe handes it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe it. But if this groſſe ſinne be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed &amp; no medicine vſed to cure it, the godly muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with grief for theſe enormities, and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that the ſacrament ſealeth vp Gods ſweete promiſes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which the wicked ſorte at no hand are partakers of.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7 The Lords ſupper muſt bee common to al the godly, not priuate to the miniſter alone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When our</hi> Sauiour Chriſt did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute the holy ſupper &amp; commend it to his apoſtles,<note place="margin">Math. chap. 26. ver. <hi>26.27</hi>
                     </note> he did neither eate &amp; drink alone for them, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded that one of them ſhoulde eate and drinke for the reſt: but he ſayde, take yee, eate yee &amp;c. Likewiſe, drinke yee all of this &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Cor. chap. <hi>10.</hi> ver. 16.</note>
                     <hi>The Apoſtle</hi> calleth the cup of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:23978:40"/>&amp;c, the communion of the bloud of Chriſt, and the bread which wee breake the communion of the bodie of Chriſt: by which wordes it is manifeſt that the holie Supper muſt bee no priuate banquet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saint Paule</hi> willeth them of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Cor. chap. 11. ver. 33.</note> when they come together to eate, to tarry one for another: which words doe euidently condemne all pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate and alone pertaking of this holye Sacrament. If any ſaye that Paules wordes proue not my purpoſe, becauſe they are to be refered to the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an loue feaſtes, my anſwere is that the Apoſtles wordes doe make greatly for my purpoſe, though it were as they fay: becauſe the feaſts of Corinth were ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the celebration of the holie communion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the time</hi> of Iuſtinus Martyr al that were preſent in the holie aſſembly did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate:<note place="margin">Apol<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>2</hi> pro Chriſt.</note> Priuate Maſſes, as yet were neither borne nor conceiued &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8 Gods people muſt not bee barred from the cup in the Lordes Supper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:40"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> at the firſt inſtitution of the holy Supper, ſaid, drinke ye al of this,<note place="margin">Math. chap. 26. ver. 27.</note> &amp;c. If the papiſts ſay that Chriſt ſpake vnto the Apoſtles onely, my anſwere is that they may as wel barre Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the bread of the Sacrament, becauſe onely the Apoſtles were parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the bread as well as of the cup, at the inſtitution of the Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let a man</hi> examine himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Cor. chap. 11. ver. <hi>28.</hi>
                     </note> and ſo let him eate of this bread and drinke of this cup, &amp;c. Saint Paule ioynes the bread and cup together: how then dare any man make a diuorce betweene the bread and the cup? Saint Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the whole body of the Church: howe dare anye man preſume to barre Gods people from the cup, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayne it to the popiſh prieſtes? The breaking of the bread and diſtributing of the cup to the communicants, are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential parts of the holy ſupper, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may not be omitted or altred.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Iuſtinus Martyres</hi> tyme, after co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration of the bread and cup,<note place="margin">Apol. 2. pro Chriſt.</note> both bread and cup were diſtributed to the communicants.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In Cyprians Ambroſes</hi> and Chriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes time,<note place="margin">Cyp. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> Theodoritus lib. 5. cap. <hi>18.</hi> Chryſoſt. in cap. <hi>8.</hi> epiſt. <hi>2.</hi> ad Corinth. Hom. 18.</note> Gods people were parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the cup in the Lords ſupper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Innocentius the 3.</hi> was the firſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhut Gods people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ſupper. He did this ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge fact in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terane councell, in the yeare of our Lorde <hi>1215.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9 What conſecration is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſecration</hi> is a dedicating to the holy vſe of the ſupper, of ſo much bread &amp; wine, as ſhal be occupied in the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the holy communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more nor leſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboliſhing of natures, but in the conuerting of the naturall eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts into a godly vſe. This is cleere in both the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the miniſter hath added the word of inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the water, it is no more common water, but baptiſme, which is a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our Regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done the like, to the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of bread &amp; wine, it is no more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon bread &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wyne, but the ſacrament of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; bloud of Chriſt Ieſus: &amp; yet the ſubſtaunce of water is not aboliſhed in baptiſme, nor the ſubſtance of bread and
<pb facs="tcp:23978:41"/>wine in the Lords ſupper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If anie</hi> ſay that the meate which is ſet on the table at dinner &amp; ſupper,<note place="margin">1. Tim. chap. 4. ver. <hi>5.</hi>
                     </note> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to a godly vſe, when it is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the worde of God &amp; prayer: I gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it to be ſo, but there is another ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, then of this in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. We obtaine by the word of God &amp; prayer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawful vſe of Gods creatures at our dinners &amp; ſuppers: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any iot of Gods firſt curſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth and fruites thereof remained, it ſhal not be hurtfull to vs: but the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; ſignes in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments become more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t things by many degrees, for by Gods worde &amp; inſtitution they are made ſignes &amp; my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our ſaluation.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10 The ſubſtance of bread and wine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the Lordes Supper after the words of Conſecration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The bread</hi> which we breake in the Lords ſupper,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Cor. chap. 10. ver. 16.</note> is it not the partaking of the body of Chriſt? Saint Paule doeth expreſſely call that which is broken, bread, not the Accidents of bread.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will not</hi> hence forth drinke of this fruite of the vine &amp;c. by the fruite of the<note place="margin">Mat. cha. 26 ver. 29.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23978:42"/>vine our Sauiour Chriſt meaneth wyne, not the accidentes of wyne. By Accidents of bread &amp; wine are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded the colour, roundnes, breadth &amp; taſt &amp;c. of bread and wyne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The worde</hi> (of inſtitution) is added to the Element and it is made a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Tract. <hi>80.</hi> in Iohan.</note> Auguſtine ſaith not, that it taketh away, or expelleth the element.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> calles that, bread, by which Chriſt repreſented his bodie.<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cont. Mar.</note> The ſame Tertullian (labouring to prooue that Chriſt had not a fantaſticall body as the Heretique Marcion imagined but a true body) reaſons thus fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Chriſt did giue bread in the ſacrament for a true figure of his body,<note place="margin">lib. <hi>4.</hi> cont. Mar.</note> therefore Chriſt had not a fantaſticall but a true bodie. If no ſubſtance of bread re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in the Lordes Supper, which the Papiſtes hold, Tertullians argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt Marcion were verye weake, and Marcions monſtrous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion were very ſtrong.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If we ſay</hi> that Chriſtes bodie is made of the ſubſtance of bread, how is it true that his body was made of the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:23978:42"/>of the bleſſed virgin:</p>
                  <p>There muſt be alwayes an Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie betweene the ſigne and the thing fignified in the ſacrament. The Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie in the holy ſupper appeareth in fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. The body &amp; bloud of Chriſt doth feed our ſoules, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread and wine doeth feed our bodies. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of bread &amp; wine bee aboliſhed, what is left to feede our bodies. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſh ſort ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of bread &amp; wine doe feede vs, they teach ſtrange, both, diuinitie and philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie: ſtraunge diuinitie, becauſe they are manifeſtly confuted by Chriſt and Paule: ſtraunge philoſphie,<note place="margin">Math. chap. <hi>26.</hi> verſe <hi>26.</hi> 1. Cor. chap. <hi>10.</hi> ver. <hi>17.</hi> Ariſt. cap. <hi>5.</hi> de ſenſu &amp; ſenſili.</note> becauſe they reuiue an olde and groſſe errour of the Pithagoreans confuted long agoe by Ariſtotle. Beſides, the Philoſophers teach vs that wee conſiſt of the ſame thinges, wherewith we are nouriſhed: If we be fedd and nouriſhed with Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, the ſubſtance of our bodies muſt conſiſt of Arcidentes. The popiſh ſorte call vs Sacramentaries, that is to ſay, ſuch as doe aboliſh the force &amp; vſe of the Sacrament: If our doctrine did ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the Analogie of the Sacrament
<pb facs="tcp:23978:43"/>is theirs doth, we might iuſtly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Sacramentaries.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> was borne in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Laterane, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeere of our Lord, <hi>1215.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt ſaid at the inſtitution of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupper,<note place="margin">Math. chap. <hi>26.</hi> ver. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </note> This is my body, therefore the ſubſtance of the bread is changed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This argument hangs together like ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp;c. If Chriſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he reached bread vnto his Apoſtles, did giue his body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally &amp; ſubſtantially to be eaten of them, then had Chriſt many reall &amp; ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tial bodies at &amp; in one &amp; the ſelfe ſame time &amp; place, which is a groſſe abſurditie: I confeſſe that Chriſtes ſpeech, this is my body, when he had giuen the bread to his Apoſtles, is a very true ſpeech: If it be a true ſpeech, it muſt bee true, either properly and literally, or figuratiuely. If it be true properly &amp; literally, then whatſoeuer may bee ſaide of Chriſtes body, (as that it was borne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed virgine, ſuffered &amp; dyed &amp; roſe againe
<pb facs="tcp:23978:43"/>&amp;c,) may be applied to the brend in the Sacramente &amp; whatſoeuer may be ſaid of the bread (as that it was ſowen, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, threſhed, baked &amp;c,) may bee like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, applied to Chriſtes bodie, which no man that feareth God can admit. If Chriſts ſpeech be vnderſtanded literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he did commaunde a foule and hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous thing, which is ſufficient to proue it a figuratiue ſpeech,<note place="margin">Leb. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>16</hi> de doct. Chri.</note> according to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtines rule. If any doe aſke me, what I take to be the true meaning of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes words, This is my body: My aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is, that they are notably expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by S. Paule, when he ſaith: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread which we breake,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 16.</note> is it not the partaking of the body of Chriſt?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If Chriſt be not bodily preſent in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, what do Gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> receiue whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are partakers of the holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> food of life &amp; immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, they eate life &amp; drink life: &amp; when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament is reached vnto them, they receiue as bread &amp; wine for the nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of their bodies, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloud
<pb facs="tcp:23978:44"/>of the Lord Ieſus for the moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table nouriſhing of their ſoules.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If any either</hi> drowned in Popery, or inclined to it, ſhall peruſe this which I haue written, I referre him for his fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruction to a notable treatiſe of Chriſts body, and bloud, writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram vnto the Emperour Charles the great. This Bertrame was both a Prieſt and a Monke, and liued in the yeare of our Lord <hi>840.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11 The wicked doe not eate Chriſtes bodie in the Sacrament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt cannot</hi> be ſeparated from his ſpirite: which ſpirite of Chriſt, becauſe the wicked haue not, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee that eateth</hi> Chriſt ſhall liue by Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn chap. 6. verſe 57. Iohn. chap. <hi>6.</hi> ver. 56. Iohn chap. 15 ver. 5.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked ſhal not liue by Chriſt. <hi>He that eateth</hi> my fleſh &amp; drinketh my bloud, abideth in me &amp; I in him. The wicked doe not abide in Chriſt, becauſe they bring not forth much fruite.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The meate</hi> of the ſoule is not eaten of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which haue not the mouth of the foule.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23978:44"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> writes that the wicked doe licke the rocke,<note place="margin">De coena Domini.</note> but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſucke from thence neyther hony nor oyle, becauſe they are quickned neither w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of charity, nor with any moyſture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſpirit: &amp; beſides, that they ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudge themſelues, nor diſcerne the ſacraments. For further proofe of this poynt, I referre the learned reader to <hi>Cyprians</hi> treatiſe of the holy Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſtion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whoſoeuer ſhall eate this bread &amp; drinke the cup of the Lord vnworthely,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Cor. chap. <hi>11.</hi> ver. 27.</note> ſhall be guiltie of the bodie and bloud of the Lord. The wicked are guiltie of the bodie &amp; bloud of the Lord, therefore the wicked doe eate the bodie &amp; drinke the bloud of the Lorde.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The argument folowes not: and the wicked are guilty of the body &amp; bloud of the Lorde, becauſe they eate &amp; drinke vnworthely the bread &amp; wine which are ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the body and bloud of the Lorde. For the iniury done to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall ſignes, reacheth to the thinges which are ſignified by them.
<pb facs="tcp:23978:45"/>If the princes cloth of eſtate be abuſed, it is a groſſe fault: and the iniury rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to the perſon of the Prince.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The wicked man is guiltie of the Lords body becauſe hee diſcerneth not the Lords body,<note place="margin">1. Cor. chap. 11. ver. 29.</note> therefore by eating Chriſtes body he is guilty.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwere.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The argument followes not: for not to diſcerne the Lords body, is, to make no difference betweene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament of Chriſtes body &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon meate: &amp; to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it, which is a groſſe ſinne, &amp; being committed againſt the ſacrament, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vnto Chriſtes body it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12 Chriſtes bodie is note uery where.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Apoſtle Peter</hi> ſaith that heauen muſt containe Chriſt vntil the time that all things be reſtored,<note place="margin">Act. chap 3. ver. 21.</note> that is to ſay, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Chriſtes ſecond comming.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Angels</hi> ſay that Chriſt is taken vp into heauen &amp;c.<note place="margin">Acts chap. <hi>1.</hi> ver. <hi>11.</hi>
                     </note> If he be taken vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen (touching his body) which muſt needs be the meaning of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels
<pb facs="tcp:23978:45"/>wordes: how is Chriſtes bodye in many places at once?</p>
                  <p>If Chriſts body be in many places at once, then Chriſts body is infinit: if it be infinite, then Chriſtes humanity is ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aboliſhed of made infinite by being turned into the godhead, which are groſſe hereſies &amp; fauour the mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Eutiches &amp; Schwe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfeldins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obiection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The diuinity &amp; humanity are vnited in Chriſt, therefore where the godhead is, the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood is likewiſe: but the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head is euery where, therefore the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is euery where.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſweare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The perſon of Chriſt</hi> is but one, and yet in doth ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt of two natures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the proprieties of ech nature doeth &amp; muſt remayne whole &amp; without confuſion to their ſeuerall natures. For to deny or confounde the proprieties,<note place="margin">Lib. 4. cont. Eutish.</note> is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde the natures. <hi>Vigilius</hi> ſaith that Chriſt is contayned in a place by the nature of his fleſhe, and is not contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in a place by the nature of his godhead.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 57. ad Dardanum.</note> Auguſtine is very ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifull &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:23978:46"/>flat for this point in one of his epiſtles.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I confeſſe that the</hi> proprieties of Chriſtes ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood may be applied to his godhead, &amp; contrarimiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his godhead, may bee applied to his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood, but yet without co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the natures: as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, Chriſtes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion doth pertaine to his fleſh according to the proprietie of nature, and if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes to the worde, that is to ſaye, Chriſtes godhead, according to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon:<note place="margin">Vigil. lib. 2. cont. Eutich.</note> becauſe there is one and the ſelfe ſame perſon both of the worde and the fleſh: ſo that whole Chriſt both: God &amp; man ſuffered according to the vnity of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſuffered not according to the propretie of nature, that is to ſay of his godhead. According to this I haue ſet downe,<note place="margin">Acts. chap. 20. ver. <hi>28. 1.</hi> Cor. chap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. 8.</note> are Saint Paules words in the Actes and to the Corinthians to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded. The councell of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople did decree that the bleſſed Virgine ſhoulde bee called the mother of GOD. We doe allowe that decree of the councell, and yet we neither doe nor may thinke that the virgine Mary did heare Chriſties Godhead in hir
<pb facs="tcp:23978:46"/>wombe: but the meaning is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was horne of the bleſſed virgine, was not onely man, but (for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction of the word to the fleſhe) God and man.</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13. The bread and wine in the Lords Supper muſt not bee reſerued for any ſuperſtitious vſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was</hi> not lawfull to keepe any part of the (Paſchall) lambe.<note place="margin">Exod. cha. <hi>12</hi> verſe <hi>10.</hi> Exod cap. <hi>16.</hi> verſe. <hi>19.20.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was</hi> not lawfull to reſerue of the Manna: That which was reſerued, was full of wormes and did ſtinke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Our Sauiour</hi> Chriſt at the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; adminiſtration of the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,<note place="margin">Mat. chap. 26. verſe 26.</note> commaunded his diſciples to take and eate, not to take and reſerue it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyprian writes</hi> that the Sacrament was receiued,<note place="margin">Decoena Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini.</note> but not ſhut vp and reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I confeſſe</hi> that the Sacrament in olde time was reſerued.<note place="margin">De lapſis lib. 6. chap. 44.</note> Cyprian wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that a certaine woman had it in her chieſt. Euſebius ſaith, out of Dionifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, that a prieſt had it in his chamber:
<pb facs="tcp:23978:47"/>where hee deliuered it to Serapions boy, to carried to Serapion which was then at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poynt of death. But this reler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Sacrament, was a ſtrange abuſe, and therefore afterwarde was iuſtly aboliſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The reſeruing</hi> and hanging vp of the Sacrament as the Papiſtes call it in a Pixe vnder a Canopie, hath no light in Gods booke to ſhewe it by: and before the time of Innocentins the fourth, it was neyther an article of our fayth, nor any lawe of the Church, that Chriſtians ſhoulde worſhip the breade &amp; wine in the Sacrament, much leſſe, giue diuine honour to a wafer cake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the action of the Sacrament is ended, if that the Popiſh Sacrament of the Altar might be accompted a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14 Howe Gods chyldren muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue themſelues, at, and after, the receiuing of the holy Supper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the</hi> time of the adminiſtration of
<pb facs="tcp:23978:47"/>the holy Supper, wee muſt vſe our eares and eyes very reuerently: our eares, in attending to Gods trueth and the holy inſtitution of the Supper: our eyes in beholding the holy miſteries ſet vpon the Lordes table. When the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is reached vnto vs, wee are weightely to conſider, that as the bread and wine is broken and powred out in the holy ſupper for our vſe: ſo Chriſts bodye and blood, which was giuen and ſhed on the croſſe for perfiting the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious woorke of our redemption, is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs to be the food of our ſoules: and for this ineſtimable benefite, wee muſt confeſſe our ſelues, to be greatly and deeply bouns to our mercifull Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, &amp; by his grace giue vp our ſelues wholie to his prayſe and ſeruice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After that</hi> our ſoules are fedd at the Lordes table, and that wee are graft in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt as into a flouriſhing vine, and ioyned to the faithfull as to goodly branches of this vine, wee muſt liue Chriſtianly not a day or two, but al our life time: firſt, in beating downe our pride &amp; vanitie: ſecondly, in doing good
<pb facs="tcp:23978:48"/>to our brethren: Laſtly, in keeping the vnitie of the ſpirit in the bond of peare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe graces</hi> if we doearneſtly pray for, to almightie God: hee will giue them vnto vs in mercie for his greater glorie, &amp; our ſingular comfort, through Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London <hi>at the three Cranes in the</hi> Vinttee, by Thomas Daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>for George Byſhoppe.</hi> 1582.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:49"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:50"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:23978:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
